Guide to the Captain William H. Fowler Papers M2098
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Captain William H. Fowler papers
circa 1917-1931
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Fowler, William H., Captain
M2098
2 Linear Feet (3 boxes, 1 flat box)
Collection of correspondence and photographs from William H. Fowler, who worked with the railroad in Russia and Northern China around the time of the Bolshevik Revolution.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was purchased by Stanford University, Special Collections in 2015.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Content Description
The materials consist of 185 handwritten letters and approximately 150-180 photographs taken by Fowler, as well as a few items of ephemera, including postcards, telegrams, War Department letters, and material related to the railway. The letters are largely sent from Harbin, China and Siberia, as well as a few from the United States. They are mostly to Fowler's wife, with whom he corresponded from 1917 to 1920, detailing for her his life in China and Russia. He describes the local populations, the conditions of the towns, cultural traits, politics, and the American forces in the areas. The Bolshevik revolution is mentioned, as well as a railroad strike in 1919. Most of the photographs are annotated with comments, and subjects include the conditions in Manchuria and Siberia, trains in Manchuria, Russian refugees, Chinese railroad workers, prisoners of war, breadlines, Russian solders marching shortly after the revolution, and American soldiers.
Biographical / Historical
William H. Fowler was a civilian recruited to serve with the American Engineering Corps division of The Russian Railroad Service Corps (RRSC) American Expeditionary Force Siberia (in this case Manchuria). The American Expeditionary Forces were involved in the Russian Civil War in Vladivostok during World War I, and after the October Revolution from 1918 to 1920. The RRSC consisted of former U.S. civilian railway workers who were organized into a military-style unit with appropriate rank to operate railroads in support of Allied forces. This force supported the Russian Provisional Government In northwestern Russia. American Transportation Corps troops maintained the railways, but in Siberia, the RRSC carried out railway operations as well as maintenance. [Information from dealer description.]
Harbin (China) -- Description and travel; Siberia (Russia) -- Description and travel; Fowler, William H., Captain
- Correspondence 1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence February - May 1918 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence June 1918 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence July 1918 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence August 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence September 1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence October 1918 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence November 1918 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence December 1918 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence January 1919 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence February 1919 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence March 1919 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence April 1919 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence May 1919 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence June 1919 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence July 1919 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence August 1919 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence September 1919 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence October 1919 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence November 1919 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence December 1919 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence 1920 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence 1931 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Correspondence undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Correspondence undated (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
- Photographs (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Clippings (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Railway Mechanical Engineer November, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Photo album, Please note this album is extremely fragile and many of the prints are almost loose. Also, due to prior water exposure many of the prints are faded or otherwise damaged. (Box 4)